So in the previous videos, we looked at how to use pivot tables for simple
तो पिछले हफ्ते के वीडियो में, हमने देखा कैसे pivot table  इस्तेमाल करना है
analysis
छोटे अनॅलिसिस के लिए
and in the following videos we are going to
और इस वीडियो में हम
really dive into all the possibilities that pivot tables have to offer. So this
देखने वाले है और सारी चीज़ें जो हम कर सकते है pivot table के साथ | तो
is what we ended up with
यह था हमारे पास
in the previous video. So what we could do now is
पिछले वीडियो में | तो अभी हम जो कर सकते है वो यह है की
add another row field, for instance add the date, and now we get a
और एक रो फील्ड जोड़ सकते है, उधारण के लिए दिनांक, और हमारे पास अभी
stacked list of rows. So we get
है एक सूची रोस की | तो हमे मिलता है
the type of beer and, underneath it, all the dates
बियर के प्रकार और उंकसे नीचे दिनांक
on which we have sold the beers. We can open and close them like a folder
जिस दिन वो बियर बिका था | हम इसे खोल सकते है और बंद कर सकते है एक
structure
फोल्डर के तरह
and we can investigate exactly at what date have we sold which beer.
और हम पता कर सकते है अच्छे से की किस दिन में हमने कौनसा बियर बेचा था |
And we can swap them too, so we can make dates the highest level,
और हम अदला बदली भी कर सकते है , हम दिनांक को उपर डाल सकते है , और फिर
and then we get for each day what are the beers we have sold
हमे मिलता है एक दिन में हमने कौनसा बियर बेचा था
at that date. And that makes it easy again
उस दिन में | और यह बहुत आसान है फिर से
to really dive into the data and understand what are my customers doing,
पता करने मेरे डेटा से की मेरे ग्राहकों को क्या कर रहे है
when are they drinking what type of drinks?
किस तरह का बियर कब वो पी रहे है?
So, so far we've only
तो अभी तक हमने बस
looked at SUMs, but we can use all types of different functions there, we don't
SUMs देखा है, पर और भी तरह के कार्य इस्तेमाल कर सकते है , हमे बस
need to use SUM.
SUM इस्तेमाल करने की ज़रूरत नही है |
There's a lot of other function that we can use if we go to the value settings
हमारे पास और भी बहुत तरीके के कार्य है जिसे हम इस्तेमाल कर सकते है अगर हम वॅल्यू सेट्टिंग्स को जाते है
below.
नीचे |
If we click them...
तो अगर हम क्लिक करते है
Yes, there we go. If you click them, you can select a lot of other fields.
आप चुन सकते है बहुत सारे और फील्ड्स |
So you see SUM, but I can also use COUNT or MIN or MAX.
तो आप देख सकते है SUM, पर मैं  COUNT या MIN या MAX का इस्तेमाल भी कर सकती हूँ |
So let's pick AVERAGE, let's pick the average amount
तो चलिए चुनते है AVERAGE को, चुनते है average
of quantity that has been sold. And what does that exactly mean,
मात्रा बियर का जिससे हमने बेचा है | पर इसका मतलब है क्या,
the average amount of quantity? It's not the average of the entire column,
average मात्रा का? यह average  नही है पूरे कॉलम का
what we get is the average per beer of whatever is in that quantity column.
जो हमे मिलता है वो यह है की, आवरेज हर एक बियर का जो है हमारे मात्रा वाले कॉलम में |
So, you can see that if we sort the values, let's sort them,
तो आप देख सकते है अगर हम मूल्यों को सॉर्ट करते है , चलिए सॉर्ट करते है,
so we can really see what's going on. Yes, there we go, we sort values and we see that some
हम देख सकते है क्या हो रहा है | हा, ये रहा, हमने मूल्यों को सॉर्ट किया है और देख सकते है की थोड़े
beers
बियर
are on average sold in a quantity of two. So we can say that the Chocolate Stout
का आवरेज बेचने वाला मात्रा दो है | तो हम कह सकते है की Chocolate Stout
is really a date beer, people buy it in duos. Whereas a Bud Light is
एक जोड़ी वला बियर है, लोग हर दम इस दो में खरीदते है | जबकि Bud Light
usually bought in bigger groups.
खरीदा जाता है जब बहुत सारे लोग एक साथ होते है |
And that sort of makes sense I guess, you buy a couple of Bud Lights for your friends, but a
और यह सॉर्ट तोड़ा समझ आता है क्यूंकी आप थोड़े Bud Light खरीदते हो अपने दोस्तों के लिए , पर एक
Chocolate Stout,
Chocolate Stout,
you might buy that for your date. So when using an
आप खरीदोगे जब आप एक डेट पे हो | तो जब हम इस्तेमाल करते है
average we look at the data in an entirely different way. We are not looking
आवरेज तो हम एक पूरे अलग नज़रीय से देखते हैं अपने डेटा को | हम नही देख रहे है
at the total
सब कुछ
but while flattening the data we are taking the average
पर एक समतल डेटा, हम आवरेज ले रहे है
for each type of beer that we sell. So in this way pivot tables allow us
हर एक तरह के बियर का जो हम बेच रहे हैं | तो इस तरह से pivot tables  हमे मौका देता है
to really dive, again I'm going to say this multiple times in this series,
डेटा में डूब जाने को, फिर से में कहती हूँ बार बार इस सीरीस में
dive into the data and help us understand
डेटा में डूब जाइए और यह हमे समझ आता है
what it actually means.
इसका असली मतलब है |